I call The Honorable Clayton Cosgrove uh
Mr Speaker I don't intend as the
national party is filibustering this
bill we intend to uh uh facilitate its
passage uh rapidly because we do support
it it is it is uh it it does make a
number of technical changes which we
support to the presedential and
Regulatory framework governing the
insurance sector I just want to Simply
touch on two points one I want to
reinforce what Mr Parker said in respect
of outstanding business uh in terms of
The Reserve Bank contemplating
increasing the credential requirements
on insur on the insurance sector from
500 to a th000 years Mr Parker did make
a good point if that translates to
increase cost and increase premium
despite the canbury earthquakes you
could have a bizarre situation where yes
potentially the insurance companies the
requirements are increased however it's
too tough for people to get insurance or
the appropriate level of insurance and
pending God forbid we have another disas
like Christ Church uh we are in a
situation under Insurance the final
thing I want to say is this though we
support this bill as a as a caner MP I
just want to say this to the insurance
industry that it is appropriate that we
uh uh protect and ensure that that
sector uh has appropriate an appropriate
regulatory framework but I bring this
message to that insurance sector from
the people of Christ Church and other
places that there is an expectation when
uh as uh kiwis who have paid insurance
premiums all our Liv collectively none
of us up until the Canter earthquake I
really thought that we would ever make a
call on that insurance unless Johnny
throws the cricket ball through the
window as it were or in a minor way that
there is a great uh almost loathing to
some extent of that sector and the
inability of that sector to appropriate
and swiftly at a high degree of
frequency pay out now I accept that the
canb earthquake is an extremely uh
complicated matter there are a number of
strands which have to be resolved but
for Mr and Mrs cantabrian S sitting in
their mted house 3 years after the event
having paid uh insurance premiums all
their lives having the insurer ring them
up if they're a day late or a week short
or whatever and making damn sure they
pay they expect that insurance companies
will pay up in the appropriate time in
most people if not all people's policies
it says words to the effect that
insurers should settle in a reasonable
period of time and I do note that uh the
prime Min of Australia when he was first
prime minister and they had the Queens
land floods came over to Christ Church
in fact labor members met with him and
we asked him is he having the same
difficulty with insurers that we are
having in terms of getting them to write
checks so people can get on with their
lives he said a f yes we asked him what
he planned to do what he did about it
and he basically said to us he called
the insurers into his office read the
riot act and threaten to regulate them
if they didn't start paying out they
reached as I understand at some sort of
voluntary voluntary time frame I know
this doesn't affect Mr Hayes voluntary
time frame and 12 months later you had
new houses being built up further up the
hill uh outside in Queensland outside
the flood prone areas we see today have
people longing to get on with their
lives charitable organizations in Christ
Church which cannot move along and are
now having to spend um many of the
charitable dollars they ordinarily would
not on overhead like rent on buildings
because the insurance company uh week
after week and year after year and
Engineering report after engineering
report will not settle and likewise with
individual cantabrians and others so I
just conclude sir by saying it is
noteworthy that this Brill looks to
predict the Regulatory and enhance the
regulat and credential framework of the
insurance sector but I say to the
insurance sector that many in this
Parliament and many new zealanders
around the country demand that they do
their bit and when the chips are down
and people have paid and they need their
lives put back together that insurance
companies pay out and pay out
swiftly uh I call The Honorable member
Julian ginta thank you Mr Speaker ten I
ra to speak on the third and last
reading of the